Hello, everyone.
I'm Karl Oprinso, a software engineer
at CreditFlow AI, and today I'll be
talking about how AI systems have
evolved and when observing our modern
AI systems, what we actually should
be looking for and what we actually
should be observing in our AI systems.
I'll spend a couple slides explaining
how I think that they are now more--
they have m-- they've now inherited
the principles of distributed systems
and also with this, what we also
should be observing for and what our
observability outcome should look like.
So I'll start with a simple mental model.
So firstly we-- previously we AI systems
were often thought to be you put your
prompt to a model and you get a response
back, and then it's very tempting to think
that is the full application actually.
But like the the-- but it's way more
than that because right now our LLMs
are m- are modern-- in modern AI
systems, l- the models are only a
part of this-- are only a part of the
systems because we have parts of the
application that runs retrieval, the
vector database, the rerankers, the cache.
In a situation where you want to do
semantic caching for a system where
you're having multiple requests, you don't
want-- you want to be able to semantically
cache that so that you're limiting
how many requests gets to your model.
So these are several working parts of
a, our current modern AI systems that
it has become more-- our LLM in-- our
LLMs have become just a part of the
systems as opposed to being the full
application as they were thought before.
The thesis of this talk basically
is like AI applications have
become distributed systems.
And what they do, they definitely would
inherit the observability problems
of observ- distributed systems, and
then the extra twist that AI LLM
systems actually bring to the the
twist that AI systems actually bring
to the table, and what we should be
observing for when we are creating
like healthy AI systems and the kind of
the drift from what we also know as a
traditional observability for AI systems.
AI systems are no longer the--
like I said, like the models are
no longer the, the models are no
longer the application anymore.
They behave as previously they used
to be just a function execution,
and then you get an output more
like we used to know where like with
bots, chatbots, where you send your
prompts, the prompt goes straight to
the model and then gets the output.
Now the surface area is a lot more.
The surface area is like there are
different workers working ab-behind.
You could have cron job.
So you tell an l an LLM, you tell like
an application, you send a prompt.
So the prompt, the LLM decides,
okay, what tool do I need to call?
D- this needs to be retrieved
from the vector database.
This needs this needs to be saved
to the ca-- this needs to be cached.
And so it has become more of a single
line, a linear one function prompt
all to get all response to different
systems, different parts of the systems
working together and having different
dependencies that like different
dependencies, different pro-- processes.
And then that introduces different things
that, that needs to be accounted for and
different failures, different, basically
different environment boundaries.
So from one system talking to another it
exposes different levels of failure, and
that we should also-- that I will talk
about how we observe for that and how
that can also lead to wrong wrong outputs.
Okay.
Basically, LLM systems are we don't
think that-- I don't think that LLM
systems are just one, one fit all.
They are now more of, they are now
more of LLMs in our models are more
like a third-party thing now, where
it's just a small part of our systems.
It's just a small part.
The LLM itself is just a small part,
but AI systems are now more distributed,
so different things are running
different parts of the system are
running to actually give us one outcome.
The model itself is no longer
the application, but our AI
systems, all we put together
becomes the application itself.
So- And what does that, sorry,
what does that what does that
bring what does that introduce?
So we know that one principle that
we can always borrow from distributed
system is that is instruments boundaries.
So from one instrument to
another, there are multiple ways
where it could fail in between.
There are a lot of like
production failures.
A lot of things can happen
between different elements.
We can have latencies, retries.
We can have model drifts.
The database can be
healthy, but the AI fails.
The tool can be fully functional,
but requesting the, the request
to the model actually failed.
So the tools were never so
the tools were never called.
So this this means like this means
that we… This means that we can
have multiple failure, and this is
actually what we build our dashboard on.
This is basically what we, this part that
it could fail, these boundaries that it
could fail, is actually where we build
our boundaries, where we actually build
our observability for AI systems on.
At this point is where we
build our observability.
So let's take let me walk you through
what a single prompt could look like.
All right?
So you, in our modern AI systems,
what a single, what happens when you
send a prompt to the system, okay?
Is that, one is that the,
the user, you ask a question.
Before it answers, the application
might have to rewrite it.
Okay?
It goes, first of all, we all know
that it goes through, currently
now, it goes through an API service,
which could have failures and the
likes, but a user send his prompt.
It goes through the model.
So the model queries,
do i-- does it query?
It queries a tool.
It queries a maybe another LLM agent
that has more specialties in, like if
it's a multimodal, if it's a multi-agent
system, it queries another prompt,
another agent to get response back,
and then it embeds it, se-sends it
to a vector database, and it sends
it to a vector database, and then it-
It sends it vector database and
then the so the model basically is
no longer operating in isolation.
The model is no longer
operating in isolation.
So because it's interacting
with so many systems, so it's no
longer operating in isolation.
It's interacting with the tools, the
vector database that we've created,
the the retrievals, the RAGs.
The model itself now, in a single
request, is interacting with different
points, different systems that
have different modes of failures
that we need to observe for.
Okay?
And here is one thing that when
you send your prompt, there are
different ways where it could fail.
And now I'm trying to create what I'm
trying to do is create the differentiation
of what and a differentiation of the
gap where we have our traditional
observability and what our current
model and what our current AI system
observability should look like.
And here is why.
Here is one reason why.
Because we could have the right answer.
Okay?
We could have the right prompt
from our user, but, and then
the, the retrieval happens.
It's a correct retrieval.
We could have the wrong
context from that retrieval.
So the model actually tries
to make a-- the model actually
tries to make that request, okay?
And It gets a wrong output from our
database, from our vector database,
and then it responds current-- it, it
responds back as a it responds back with
confidence, but it's a wrong answer.
So here's another situation where
we have a good retrieval, we have
a good context, but then it's--
the model just hallucinates, okay?
So the model we get like the model
just guesses based on maybe a poor--
there, there was a poor context.
So okay, we have a, a good retrieval,
poor context, and then the model
just has like just guesses.
So we see now that the, there
are different ways where this
interaction brings failure.
There are different points where
And when we're observing, we should…
These are like some things that
we should be observing for like
out, like what was the retrieval?
What was the-- what was retrieved?
What was the prompt?
What was retrieved?
What was our tool saying?
And what was the model
actually retrieving?
What was the model reading of our
context prompt, and what was the output?
So these are different points.
These are different parts where
we are reading for, reading
from, okay, or reading for.
So here's what a, a a trace would look
like when you send a prompt, okay?
Like previously I was telling you,
previously I was mentioning the… I gave
a graphical view of, I gave how a prompt
takes from what a prompt is from the end
user, from the user to the finish point.
So this is what a trace
actually does look like.
So it's no longer a… A trace
is now more of a decision path
as opposed a request path.
So it's, yes, it's a request path, but
it's more of how decisions were made.
It's more of how the decision of
that final output, the probabilities,
areas where it could have failed,
what outputs, like what output
actually led to that final output?
What output actually led to that
final outcome, that final answer
from our from our application.
So we have the retrieval happens.
So it depends on how you
build out your AI systems.
But more of it's more like the
retrieval happens, embeddings,
then it goes to the LLM.
If LLM calls a tool for retrieval
or calls a tool for more context or
calls a tool for accurate data, and
then it gives you your final tool.
Now traces are now more of decision.
So when we are building out our
observability, we also want to have the--
we want to have that knowledge that you're
not, we're not building our observability
for… we're not building our
observability for just what's it called?
We're not building our observability
for just how the system is
operating, how the, the CPU is.
Is the system, the uptime of the
system, the availability of the system.
But we're building how it-- we're building
observability for how it came to that
conclusion, how the decisions were made.
Okay?
So next is what's our
traditional data path?
So with building we've seen that
our requests, our traces are now
more of how decisions are taken as
opposed how the, just how the service
is operating, how the, the uptime
of the system, the availability.
So it has created a gap that we, when
we are building, we need to be aware of.
Okay?
So the application, the infrastructure
dashboard could be green, the latency
is good, the error rate is low, the
CPU is normal, availability is high.
And from a normal observability
perspective, this system
looks very healthy.
So the qu- the… But when we are
building our system, there are a couple
things that we need to measure for.
We need to know if it's grounded.
So grounded, when we say
grounded, it's like, is it high?
Is it correct?
Is it really grounded in the
context that we've given it?
Is it, if let's say you have a database
that you're retrieving from fi- financial
informations or informations based on
the person, is this answer actually
based on that human or based on the
context that we've given the, the LLM?
So for example you have a
database that have the name, the
date of birth, and the the year basically.
So if your LLM, if you query, if your
te- your OpenTel, if your telemetric,
your observability is not actually able
to tell when an agent i- is retrieving
the wrong year from is retrieving
the y-- wrong year from the database,
then it's a broken observability.
So when we're building observ-- when
we're building an observability stack
for an for an AI system, we want to be
able to accommodate for, we want to be
able to build these extra parts that
make the AI system actually observed.
Okay?
So the, the-- and here's the contradiction
it's not here is the thing, not really
a contradiction, but here is the thing,
is like the traditional telemetries
asking like if the system, if it
was actually executed properly, if
the request went through everything
that it was supposed to go through.
Is it healthy?
Is the latency within like the
agreements or is it leveled?
But AI system don't ask that.
What what AI system is actually asking
is like, did it produce a good result?
Okay.
The distinction is basically AI
observability does not stop at, it doesn't
just stop at infrastructure metrics.
It actually wants-- when we're
observing an AI system, we want to
know was the output good enough?
Okay.
So here is how the AI observability
how AI observability extends.
Okay.
I think I like to think of the
solution in three layers, okay?
So one is at the bottom, we keep
the normal system telemetry, the
l-latency, the errors, the throughput,
the saturation, the availability.
But above that layer, we want to add we
add AI-specific execution, like telemetry.
So for this execution telemetry, we
know that we need to know the model.
So we can also check, okay is it
because the model has drifted?
Is it because the model is out of
touch, out of use, or is deprecated
that resulted to a fault, okay?
We also want to know the
tokens that generate.
What's the amount of tokens?
Is the-- is it too much
that resulted to an error?
We want to know the prompts that
came in, that went in and came out.
Like we can-- so we are able to
compare outputs and out, and inputs.
And then the retrieval results, what was
retrieved, the tools that were called
the accuracy of those tools, and then
the tool results, the cost, and other
context around an expected behavior.
So we were able to measure.
That would help us be able to measure
the AI system as itself, okay?
When we're building the
observability stack for an AI system.
Then on top of that is just
quality signals, basically,
like groundedness, relevance.
So based on the telemetry that
we've gotten, we're able to build.
Then we go ahead to build the AI quality.
So these are the three metrics that
when building observability for an,
like a distributed AI system, we want
to think about is, one, you want to
have the normal, you want to have the
normal telemetry that we always have.
Then you want to have the open AI,
the AI-specific telemetries, and
then the quality on top of, and
then the quality on top of that.
So we, like I mentioned earlier,
is that AI observability normally
acts like what happened while the
evaluation on top of every or all
of that acts like, was it good?
Did we get like the best out of it?
Was it ground-- were the results grounded?
Were the did we get the--
was the result grounded?
Was it relevant to the prompt?
Were the answers relevant to the prompt?
And I think that this, this is, this
idea basically is how most of our--
most tools are actually now built.
Most of these observabilities
like Langfuse, Phoenix Arize AI.
I think this is how, is the phil- is this
philosophy that that they use to build
these observability tools that we can
use to actually observe our AI systems.
But the ideology still
remains in the same.
If when we're observing an AI system upon
the normal observability telemetry, we
want to know if the-- it's grounded in the
context, if it's relevant, if it's obeying
the guardrails that has been set, if it's
not, so that it doesn't fall, like provide
breaking the EU laws or exposing personal
information, PP- PIs and the likes, okay?
So that's what our observability,
when we're building observability
for AI system, that's one
thing we want to take note of.
And since there are d-different
systems that are producing that
information, we want to be aware that
no one is breaking any of these, okay?
And all are being, like observed.
So So one thing is that like
I mentioned, like we have the
trace, the normal telemetry, we
have the evaluation pipelines.
And these evaluation pipelines can be
your CI, where after making changes
to your vector database or making
changes to your-- making changes to a
tool, you have a CI that is actually
checking for based on your dataset or
datasets that you have, that is actually
checking for these that's actually
checking if everything falls in line.
Okay?
Actually checking if your observability
is act- if your observability, if your,
sorry, if your application actually
obeys those laws that you've set out.
So I think basically what I'm just,
what I'm just trying to communicate
here is that we want to treat the
evaluation as… We don't want to
treat it as just one we don't want to
treat it as just one, one meta fit all.
We want to be able to, we want to be
able to regularly check when building
observ-- We want to be able to regularly
check because there could be drift
in the model, there could be failure.
But we want to be like intentionally
check this, not be stuck to one vendor.
Just have a system that is able to
check is able to check our application
regularly to know where is…
So it could be maybe a, it could
be a cron job that runs it could
be a cron job that runs after a
request has gone through, okay?
Or it could be a cron job
that runs a, a request hourly.
I think that's like what I've seen, where
it runs like hourly to know if things
are still, if there hasn't been any,
if or if, for example, if you make a
change to your prompts and your schemas,
you run a CI, it actually checks these,
these changes to know that at the end
outcome is still what is expected based
on like certain datasets and all that
here's a couple checklist that when
like, when designing observability for
AI systems, we want to take note of.
First is we want to be
able to preserve causality.
In this situation, we want to be
able to keep the i-identity across
different services, different tools,
different workers, different evaluation.
We want to be able to the traces and
the-- We want to be able to keep that.
The second we want to have, we want
to know the instrument boundaries.
Where are these latencies, okay?
Where were we we want to be able to
know where the retry happened, where
the, there was a state mismatch,
where there was external failure,
where a third party failed, okay?
The third is the we want to be
able to trace the decision path.
Like I mentioned, what a decision
path is where we want to know
if, like, where the retrieval.
We want to know the retrieval, we
want to know the context, we want to
know the calls, the tool calls, the
outputs, the and not just timing, not
just uptime, not just availability.
We want to know when we're building a,
when we're building a design, when we're
designing our observability for AI system,
we want to be able to know all of that.
We also want to be able to separate
a health system from an AI quality.
So a health system, like I mentioned,
is like there's 200 your request lands
properly, but the quality is low.
So we want to be able to we want
to be able to differentiate this
when building observability system.
Like I mentioned I think, like I
mentioned about the CI or depending
on how you decide to run your ob
observability, like I, I mentioned
using CI to run your observability.
We want to be able to measure the quality
of the-- We want to measure the quality
of the outputs as opposed to just the
system the system, the, the operationality
of the system, we want to be able to
we want to be able to separate that.
So they are two different things.
Th-that's one principle we
should know is like they are
separate things entirely, okay?
And finally, we want to remember
that telemetry itself is a system,
is like a production system.
So the sampling, the access control,
the versioning, and all of this, we want
to be able to store them separately.
We want to be able to have them
versioned so that we can always come
back to see the progress of how the,
how our system is actually progressing.
Is it regressing from our expected
output or it's progressing,
we're having more of that?
So w- when you're designing your
observability you need to take that whole,
the operation as a stack of its own, okay?
And able to measure it going forward
and backward, the regress and version
control, what happened, and then a
w- like one that matches your dataset
or like maybe human, happy path human
feeling, and then you stick with that.
Okay.
So I think that's one real principle
that, and rule that when designing
around, you should also be be mindful of.
Okay.
And this is my last slide, and one
thing I want to talk about is just
to bring all, all this together.
Okay.
To bring all this together is that-
When we have three phases, one is that
we want to trace the path, and this
is a traditional level where we want
to know what happened, where did it
happen, and then what caused it, okay?
And then we want to be able to
also measure the system, okay?
Is it-- was it fast?
Was it reliable?
And how did the dependencies be?
How are the systems depending?
Where is the vector database?
What's providing the… How is
the vector database performing?
How is it behaving?
So we want to be able to measure the
system, and then we want to, at the
end, be able to evaluate the outcome.
We want to be able to,
is the answers correct?
Is it grounded?
And did the user actually find it useful?
And I think, like I said, like
one way to actually achieve this
is using like a CI infrastructure
where, or an observability tool.
Or if you're just starting out, a CI
infrastructure where you can, you have
some datasets that you can use to prompt
your system to know how that, that
would let it run through the tools,
run through the applica- run through
the tools, run through the embedding,
the vector database and the likes of
like the application, and know if the
desired output is what you're having.
Okay?
And so this is how I like to think about
AI build-- when building AI systems and
AI systems of ob-observability, okay?
It's now, it has passed the function,
just one function solving every
issue and the model being the primary
focus of our application to a point
where it's different systems working
together to actually give a defined
output and how we're able to observe.
And so that, that actually lets
me, the… and I think in this
situation, you to build when building
observability to know what matters
and build them the the right way.
Build them a way that it is
now actually really functional.
It's actually now useful for, to
evaluate users and evaluate how
we are building the application.
If it actually serves the need or
the product that we were… like
the outcome that we're looking
to get from our application.
So I think that basically it's just,
this is just a mental model and practical
ways that we can go ahead to build.
And if you want to reach me you
can reach me on Kaleb Princewill
on LinkedIn, primarily on LinkedIn
or kalebprince1@gmail.com,
and we can discuss from there.
Thank you.